Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 1. Governance, administration, and 3-School affairs (1888-2016; 64.42 linear feet), 216900; 64.42 Linear feet
  - Series IV. Office of the 3-School Director, 1937-1999; 223145; 23 Linear feet
    - Subseries IV.D Office of the Director - Wagner through Tofel, 1937-1978 (bulk 1957-1973); 223830
      - Director's files P-R (15 folders), 1950-1973; 223831 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 27-41)
        File list: Director's correspondence - P, Parents (role of), Harvard Project Physics, Planning-Programing-Budgeting, Playschool Association, Principals, Publications (ads in, Ethical Culture Society), Publications Review Committee, Publications of staff members, Director's correspondence - R, Remedial reading, ESC Reporter.
      - Director's files R-S (31 folders), 1952-1973; 223832 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-31)
        File list: Rhythms, Riverdale Coastal Community, Riverdale Neighborhood Association, Riverdale Community Council, Riverdale Community House, Committee on Rules, Director's papers - S, Thomas Scheuer, Scholarship loan policy, 3-Schools, Finance, Salary schedule, Salary negotiations, Schools and Ethical Culture Society, School law course, Committee on School plant requirements, Committee on 12 month school year, Science, Senior year-end projects, Sex and family life, Sex and family relations, Sinaiko property, Social security, Social studies, Songs, Speak Out, Speeches made, Special projects - administrative procedures, Special program school - slow learning, Strike letter sent to parents.
      - Director's files S-W (35 folders), 1949-1973; 223833 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-35)
        File list: Student political affairs, Sutro Price estate, Student rosters, SUNY State Education Department, Director's papers - T, Task force - disadvantaged children, Tate Library (acquisitions committee, forum, statements, development, materials), Teacher training, Teaching trends, Television, Tenure, Tests, TIAA, Transportation, Tuition rise letters, Tutoring rates, Director's papers - U, Unemployment insurance, Use of Schools (Greystone Avenue), United/Major medical insurance, UNCF, Director's papers - V, Visitors, Director's papers - W, Wage freeze, Wave Hill.
      - Sinaiko property, 1963-1972; 224645 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 36)
      - Industrial Arts Committee, 1959; 224608 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 37)
      - Application for employment form, 1966; 224609 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 38)
      - African-American students (2 folders), 1965, 1970; 224611 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 39-40)
      - Development department (12 folders), 1954-1978; 223834 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1-12)
        Files related to fund-raising, gifts, and the School's work with funds and foundations.
      - Publicity department (5 folders), 1956-1977; 223835 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 13-17)
        Includes press releases and correspondence.
      - Parent and Teacher Association, 1973-1976; 223836 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 18)
      - Alumni Association (5 folders), 1952-1966, 1977; 223837 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 19-23)
        Primarily concerned with alumni fund-raising.
    - Subseries IV.E Office of the Director - Aron through Radest, 1970-1986; 224198
      Materials created by and during the tenure of director Jerome Aron, interim director Carol Tofel, and director Howard Radest (mostly by Tofel and Radest). Types of materials frequently seen include correspondence, reports, and committee documents. Finances and budgets are a frequent theme in records throughout this subseries.
      - Director's correspondence (6 folders), 1977-1979; 224204 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 24-29)
        Correspondence of Directors Carol Tofel and Howard Radest, with administration, Board members, and public.
      - Director's correspondence (7 folders), 1979-1981; 224207 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1-7)
      - Parent dialogues with Dr. Radest (7 folders), undated; 224211 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 8-14)
        Sign-up forms and notes from parent discussion topic meetings.
      - Development (9 folders), 1975-1979; 224212 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 15-23)
        Materials primarily related to the Ethical Fieldston Fund, along with a small amount on endowment funds and bequests.
      - Budgets (9 folders), 1974-1981; 224214 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 24-32)
        Annual budgets, materials created in preparation of budgets, and related correspondence.
      - Audits (2 folders), 1978-1979; 224217 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1-2)
      - New York State aid (5 folders), 1974-1979; 224218 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 3-7)
        Applications for aid and related correspondence.
      - Buildings and grounds (6 folders), 1975-1981; 224220 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 8-13)
        Maintenance, expenses, and the use of facilities.
      - Computers (4 folders), 1979-1984; 224224 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 14-17)
        Research and correspondence on technology purchases.
      - Faculty negotiations (14 folders), 1972-1980; 224227 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 18-31)
      - Business office (2 folders), 1974-1978; 224228 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1-2)
      - Ethics Department (5 folders), 1975-1980; 224232 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 3-7)
        Correspondence and reports.
      - Questionnaires (2 folders), 1976-1978; 224246 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 8-9)
        ECS responses to external questionnaires.
      - Subject files (16 folders), 1972-1983; 224251 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 10-25)
        File list: Academy of Independent Scholars, Board of Governors, Church-State issue, Employment aids, Fieldston Day Camp, Food service, Government and schools, Ira Greiff, NAIS Conference, Parent and Teacher Association, Personnel directories, Publications, Purchase orders, Shrinkage of Fieldston Lower, Teaching Staff, Television.
      - Development - "The Case for the Ethical Culture Schools" (4 folders), 1978-1980; 224612 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 20-23)
      - "Black Awareness Program" (2 folders), 1970-1975; 224613 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 24-25)
      - Administrative structure (2 folders), 1984, 1986; 224614 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 26-27)
    - Subseries IV.F Office of the Director - Radest through Amster, 1973-1999; 224285
      Materials created by and during the tenure of directors Howard Radest and Jeanne Amster during the 1980s and early 1990s. Many items were created by assistant director Ellen Edwards and business managers Joseph Estenes and Robert Dicker.
      Files are largely arranged chronologically.
      - Faculty Interest Committee and negotiations (7 folders), 1981-1989; 224287 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 26-32)
      - Salaries and administrative structure (8 folders), 1973-1990; 224615 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-8)
      - Committees (5 folders), 1980-1984; 224616 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 9-13)
        Bricks and Mortar Sub-Committee, Evaluation Committee, Financial Aid Sub-Committee, Financial Aid and Enrollment Committee, Instruction Sub-Committee.
      - Faculty Conference Day, 1982; 224617 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 14)
      - Radest correspondence and plans (2 folders), 1981-1988; 224618 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 15-16)
      - Budgets and expenses (3 folders), 1985-1989; 224619 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 17-19)
      - Jeanne Amster papers (4 folders), 1989-1992; 224620 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 20-23)
        Ethical-Fieldston Fund, graphic design, new finance director.
      - Computer technology (3 folders), 1995-1996; 224621 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 23-25)
        New York State Association of Independent Schools technology group and computer purchase program records. 1996-2000 Technology Plan.
      - Strategic Planning: Surveys (3 folders), 1999; 224622 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 26-28)
        Survey result data tables.
      - Various Director's files (12 folders), 1973-1993 (Offsite-box 56, Folder 11-22)
        File names: Fire drills, Nuclear war, Riverdale apartments, Riverdale Mental Health Association, Emergency school procedures, NYU, Midtown safety, Teaching on the Hill, Public/private partnerships (2 folders), Retirement committee, Albert G. Oliver Program, Minority teachers/enrollment, Midtown, Fieldston Lower, Fieldston.
      - Various Director's files (14 folders), 1976-1994 (Offsite-box 57, Folder 1-14)
        Files include: Parent and Teacher, Endowment, Faculty Development Committee, Coordinating Committee, Tenure Committee, Structure, Faculty correspondence (3 folders), Lincoln Center Institute, Chart of Accounts, Encampment for Citizenship, Transportation, Parent Handbook, Guidance, Board of Governors (and committees), Inter-school organizations, June Weeks, School/Society meetings, Midtown, Fieldston.
      - Various Director's files (19 folders), 1980-1993 (Offsite-box 58, Folder 1-19)
        Files relating to after-school and summer programs, financial matters, the Learning Styles Committee, the Music Committee, and the Sutro Fund.
      - Various Director's files (9 folders), 1977-1986 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 1-9)
        Files include: Weis Ecology Center, Ethical Culture Retirement Center, Properties, Music Committee, Fieldston Principal Search, and various financial related.
  - Series V. Admissions and registration, 1888-2010; 216905; 13 Linear feet
    This series includes materials related to the enrollment of students across the 3-Schools, with topics including scholarships and registration.
    This series is divided into two subseries:
    Subseries V.A. Admissions and scholarships
    Subseries V.B. Lists of students
    - Subseries V.A Admissions and scholarships, 1905-1982; 217041
      Files include scholarships committee materials, reports on overall registration, and discussion of admissions and enrollment procedures. The subseries does not include specific applications for enrollment or scholarships.
      Arranged by type of document, then chronologically within each type.
      - Application procedures, 1974, 1981, undated; 224646 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1)
      - Scholarship and Admissions Committees (16 folders), 1905-1961; 224647 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 2-17)
        Minutes, correspondence, and lists of students receiving or requesting scholarships. Earlier files include discussion of individual scholarship requests, student performance, and family need. Files after 1945 are primarily lists. Includes 1941 letter from Arthur Hays Sulzberger.
      - Reports of the Director of Admissions (5 folders), 1967-1982; 224648 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 18-22)
        Titled Reports of the Registrar until 1974. Reports including information such as number students attending, percentage accepted, income from tuition, sibling and alumni enrollment, and diversity in student body.
      - Miscellaneous enrollment documents, 1924-1965; 224651 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 23)
        Correspondence and memorandum.
      - Scholarship grade books, 1931-1939 (Offsite-box 308)
        Six oversize gradebooks, with chart of letter grades for scholarship students in each subject.
      - Scholarship grade books, 1939-1945 (Offsite-box 309)
        Five oversize gradebooks, with chart of letter grades for scholarship students in each subject.
      - Scholarship grade books, 1945-1955 (Offsite-box 310)
        Ten oversize gradebooks, with chart of letter grades for scholarship students in each subject.
    - Subseries V.B Lists of students, 1888-2010; 217043
      Lists of students by grade for each year. For most years, lists include student and parent names, addresses and telephone numbers (and sometimes professions). Many rosters list entire student body, but those divided into classes also include information such as teacher, assistant and class chairman names. Varying types of other information included for some years, such as lockers numbers, or a faculty directory. 1944-1959 onward, rosters include addresses (and sometimes professions) of parents.
      - Class lists (13 folders), 1891-1932; 224686 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1-13)
      - Class lists and student rosters (17 folders), 1927-1959, 1964-1965, 1971-1973; 224687 (Offsite-box 32, Folder 1-17)
      - Class lists and student rosters (19 folders), 1973-1989; 224688 (Offsite-box 33, Folder 1-19)
      - Class lists and student rosters (9 folders), 1988-1995 (Offsite-box 34, Folder 1-9)
      - Class lists and student rosters (9 folders), 1986-2010; 224689 (Offsite-box 54, Folder 1-9)
      - Class tuition lists (7 folders), 1943-1962; 224690 (Offsite-box 315, Folder 1-7)
        Lists of students indicating those who pay full tuition, and those on scholarship (with percentage of tuition paid).
      - Graduation lists (4 folders), 1888-1968; 224691 (Offsite-box 315, Folder 8-11)
        Up to 1900, all are elementary school graduates; 1901-1903, no graduates yet because first high school class still progressing. 1904 onward, all lists reflect high school graduation. 1925-1968 records list address. 1958-1968 records list colleges attending. Graduation brochures for some later years.
      - Visitors lists (Guest registers), 1928-1958; 224652
        Four books with handwritten lists with date, name, residence, and purpose of visit.
  - Series VI. Faculty and staff, 1901-2006; 216907; 6.5 Linear feet
    This series contains records of both individual employees (3-School and individual schools) as well as records addressing issues and policies that affect faculty and staff as a whole.
    This series is arranged in two subseries:
    Subseries VI.A Faculty and administration personnel files
    Subseries VI.B Faculty matters
    - Subseries VI.A Faculty and administration files, circa 1901-1994; 217056
      This subseries consists of individual files for faculty and staff. For the majority of individuals, materials consist of one folder relating to their employment and work at the Ethical Culture Schools. Nearly all materials in the series were created between 1920 and 1950. (The small amount of items created in the 1970s through the 1990s are mostly obituaries or memorial items for past faculty.) The series is arranged alphabetically by last name.
      Files of teachers and principals are most commonly found, but the series also contains several files for psychologists and guidance counselors, librarians, medical staff (especially dieticians and nurses), facilities staff, secretaries, and business managers. Both 3-School staff and staff from individual schools are included.
      Correspondence, both with and regarding the individual, makes up the bulk of the series. Letters typically discuss administrative matters, classroom issues, contracts, salaries, requests for supplies, and facilities issues. The majority of correspondence is internal to the Schools, along with instances of correspondence with vendors or colleagues at other educational institutions. Many correspondence items concern employment, including inquiries into work at the Ethical Culture Schools, requests by Fieldston for references or other information about a prospective employee, or requests for references by other schools. There are some examples of personal correspondence, such as invitations, or notes keeping in touch with past employees.
      Other than correspondence, files contain curriculum items, schedules, summer contact information cards, news clippings, ephemera, and classroom materials (syllabi, bibliographies). Obituaries, memorial service programs and other tribute materials are found throughout. There is some discussion of specific students, before 1950.
      The personnel files for some individuals do contain substantive materials about the work of their department. In particular, the folders of Henry Kelly (14 folders, 1902-1939), August Klock (7 folders, 1923-1940) contain a good deal of information about the biology department, including the report "The Science Course at Fieldston," 1930. The following files contain information about each department, mostly during the 1930s and early 1940s: Margaret Koch, history; William Kurtz, physical education and athletic programs; Ethel Murphy, math; Alberta Newton, Greek and Latin. The two files of Arthur Richards contain information on the printing shop in the 1920s. Other departments represented include English, ethics, chemistry, fine arts, French, and German.
      This subseries is arranged alphabetically by last name.
      - Adams-Goodkind (137 folders), 1925-1978; 224855 (Offsite-box 35, Folder 1-137)
      - Goodlander-Klock (86 folders), 1925-1976; 224856 (Offsite-box 36, Folder 1-86)
      - Klock-Lenrow (40 folders), 1919-1961, 1993; 224857 (Offsite-box 37, Folder 1-40)
      - Leonard-Porcelli (91 folders), 1920-1956, 1993; 224858 (Offsite-box 38, Folder 1-91)
      - Porter-Willard (106 folders), 1924-1957, 1994; 224861 (Offsite-box 39, Folder 1-106)
      - Wilkes-Zim (14 folders), 1901-1953, 1994; 224862 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 1-14)
    - Subseries VI.B Faculty matters, 1903-2006; 217057
      This subseries includes materials relating to issues affecting the 3-School faculty and staff, including training, salaries and professional development. Some additional miscellaneous faculty-related materials can be found, including biographies and event ephemera.
      - Faculty handbooks (9 folders), 1948-1966, 1982-1996; 224864 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 15-23)
        Handbooks for new teachers, with introductory information on the history and organization of the schools, and instructions and regulations for the classroom and administrative matters.
      - Articles written by and about faculty (3 folders), 1928-1986, undated early 1900s; 224865 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 24-26)
      - Faculty directories and new staff bios (10 folders), 1944-2001; 224866 (Offsite-box 40, Folder 27-36)
      - Administrative affairs, circa early 1900s, 1981-1991; 224875 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 1)
      - Salaries and benefits (2 folders), 1951-1992; 224876 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 2-3)
        Includes records related to the Faculty Interest Committee.
      - Professional development and regulations (2 folders), 1903-2002; 224877 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 4-5)
      - Miscellaneous (4 folders), 1935-2006; 224878 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 6-9)
        Includes communications to faculty from the administration, and 1975-1976 faculty schedules.
  - Series VII. Miscellaneous, 1928-2016; 216908; 2.92 Linear feet
    - Office of the Director of Related Programs and Campus Operations (16 folders), 2000-2016 (Offsite-box 61, Folder 1-16)
      Bulk of materials created 2011-2015. Most materials related to the rental of school facilities by outside groups. Some materials concern vendors providing services to the school, especially transportation. Types of materials include print matter from other institutions or vendors, correspondence (printed email), reports, and contracts. Also includes the 2014 International Program Emergency Response Manual.
    - Song books (5 folders), 1934-1942, undated (Offsite-box 300, Folder 28-32)
      Lyrics and sheet music for school songs and others sung at school and Ethical Culture Society events. Includes 1942 copy of the Fieldston Lower Song Book, printed on the school's press, four undated copies of Songs for the Lunchroom.
    - Guest registers (3 folders), 1928-1958 (Offsite-box 300, Folder 33-35)
      Visitors to Fieldston, 1928-1929. Guests 1932-1958. Father's Day and other visitors, 1943-1957.
    - Visitors register, 1929-1933 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous oversize (2 folders), 1944-1993, undated (Offsite-box 62, Folder 10-11)
      Collection of teacher Augustus Klock materials, design materials for memorial for teacher Patricia Norman, art prints.
    - Founder's Day (5 folders), 1935-2001 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 10-14)
      Mostly programs and other ephemera. Includes texts of some addresses, and 1970s planning materials.
    - Guidance department (3 folders), 1951-1974 (Offsite-box 41, Folder 15-17)
      Meeting materials, departmental annual reports, and correspondence.
    - 3-School Parent & Teacher Association, 1981-1990 (Offsite-box 42, Folder 1)
    - Dues Paid books, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 42, Folder 3)
      List of names--likely Alumni Association.
    - Miscellaneous administration (17 folders), 1960-2003 (Offsite-box 42, Folder 3-19)
      Various files, most created by the 3-School administration. Subject include organization of the schools, finances, minority students, handbooks, strategic planning, and technology.
    - Miscellaneous (7 folders), 1937-2017 (Offsite-box 59, Folder 15-21)
- Record Group 2. Early and defunct schools (1879-1957; 13.17 linear feet), 216919; 13.17 Linear feet
  This record group includes materials for the Ethical Culture School and its programs prior to the opening of the Fieldston campus in 1928. This includes records for the earlier iteration of the school, The Workingman's School, and its evolution to Ethical Culture Schools. The record group also contains records for discontinued early programs: the Summer Play School, the Open Air Department, and the Normal Department for Teacher Training.
  Types of materials include ephemera, correspondence, reports, student work, photographs, and news clippings. Board records and administrative records from this era can be found in Record Group 1, and additional ephemera can be found in Record Group 11, Printed matter.
  Arrangement
  This record group is organized into four series:
  Series I. Defunct schools
  Series II. Ethical Culture Schools
  Series III. Normal Teacher Training Department
  Series IV. Normal School student records (RESTRICTED)
  - Series I. Defunct schools, 1883-1927; 216922; 1 Linear feet
    This series includes records for early schools and programs that are no longer in existence: the Workingman's School, the Open Air School, and the Summer Play School. (The Branch School was also in operation during this era, but collection does not contain any related records.) These early records mostly consist of ephemera and reports from teachers and principals, along with four scrapbooks compiled by Summer Play School leader Mabel Towne Burnham.
    The Open Air Department conducted classes on the roof of the Central Park West Building from the 1910s through the 1920s. The Summer Play School was founded in partnership with the New York Federation for Child Study (later the Child Study Association of America) in 1919, providing summer activities and meals for underprivileged children at the Ethical Culture School building on Central Park West.
    Within this series, files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Workingman's School - Rules and regulations for pupils, circa 1890, 1893; 217067 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 1)
      Printed pamphlets with school rules.
    - Workingman's School - Festival and event programs, 1891, 1894; 217069 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 2)
      Printed programs for festivals and an "open school" day.
    - Workingman's School - Student work and monthly student reports, 1886-1891, undated; 217070 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 3)
      One example of each, for student Gertrude Prince.
    - Workingman's School - Graduation programs, 1891, 1892; 217071 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 4)
    - Workingman's School - Mechanical Drawing curriculum book, 1892; 226718 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 5)
      Book with diagrams and notes on program. Title page inscribed, "May 1, 1892. Course for the Workingman's School. Mechanical Drawing, Work Instruction, and Factory Excursions. Joseph L. Bedford." Includes 1991 note from Herbert S. Zim to Howard Radest on donation of book.
    - Workingman's School - Handbook for the World's Fair, 1892; 226722 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 6)
      Manuscript with history and description of the Workingman's School, typecast by school.
    - Workingman's School - Weekly reports (4 folders), 1883-1889; 226723 (Offsite-box 50, Folder 7-10)